The דף daf is מ"ט. mem tet. We pick up with top
of
מ"ט עמוד א'. mem tet amud aleph. We actually are even a
few lines ahead and we are in the middle of discussing הטמנה
hatmanah about insulating food before שבת, Shabbat, but we are also going
to see as we turn to the עמוד ב' amud bet in
a slight digression of the גמרא Gemara a turn to a really
like Bavli-central discussion of שבת. Shabbat. So we'll have you that as
a little cliffhanger. Let's start from four lines from the top, בזמן
שהן לחין, bizman shehen lachin, by the two dots, when they are
moist. These are various types of things that can be used when
they are dry but not when they are moist, presumably when they
are moist they give off heat. Again, not exactly sure, somehow the
water interacting with the material somehow releasing some heat. Okay, these are
things such as it says straw and you know pieces of cloth
and grass etc. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. איבעיא
להו, ibayu lehu, they raised the question. לחין מחמת עצמן או דלמא
לחין מחמת דבר אחר? lachin machmat atzman o dilma lachin machmat davar
acher? Are they moist because they themselves originally were moist or are
they moist because they absorbed moisture from elsewhere, presumably with an assumption
that if they absorbed moisture from elsewhere they will not give off
as much heat. I really don't know the science, if there is
a science to this, and if it is I don't know what
it is. But okay, that's what the גמרא Gemara assumes. תא שמע,
ta shema, come and hear. לא בתבן ולא בזגין ולא במוכין ולא
בעשבין, lo beteven velo bezagin velo bemochin velo beasavin, you can't use
like straw and pieces of cloth and grass בזמן שהן לחין, bizman
shehen lachin, if they are moist. אי אמרת בשלמא לחין מחמת דבר
אחר שפיר, ee amrat bishlama lachin machmat davar acher shapir, I understand
how these can be moist from some other thing, you know some
water spilled on them, they absorbed moisture, that I get.
אלא אי אמרת לחין מחמת עצמן מוכין מחמת עצמן היכי משכחת לה?
ela ee amrat lachin machmat atzman mochin machmat atzman heichi mishkachat lah?
How do you get pieces of cloth that have their own moisture?
Right, where did,
you know, where did pieces of cloth get moisture from? Obviously they
absorbed moisture from elsewhere. So the גמרא Gemara has an answer. No,
ממרטא דביניתמי, mimarta deben itmi, from the like wool that comes from
רש"י Rashi says from like the thigh area of the sheep and
therefore the wool is always like a moist type of a wool.
So, you know, I don't exactly get that that's מחמת עצמן, machmat
atzman, that's still from the sheep's, you know, perspiration or whatever, but
somehow since it was like originally part of it, that is somehow
seen as an example of its own moisture. So the גמרא Gemara
says והא דתני רבי אושעיא, veha detani Rabi Oshaya, so how about
what רבי אושעיא Rabi Oshaya taught in a ברייתא. baraita. טומנין בכסות
ובפירות, tomnin biksut uvefirot, you can use old clothes to, you know,
to insulate because again it doesn't add heat. ובפירות יבשין, ubeirot yeveshin,
dried fruit. Now fruit, you think what, apples? So רש"י Rashi says
it's actually coming up in the משנה, Mishnah, רש"י Rashi says no,
small little fruit like beans or what do you call it or
like wheat flour... flour
is considered פירות? peirot? Yeah,
okay. רש"י Rashi actually says חיטין, chitin, I'm sorry, so wheat. Okay
anyway, and dried fruit. אבל לא בכסות לחה, aval lo bichsut lacha,
not with a moist garment ולא בפירות לחין, velo bepeirot lachin, and
not with moist fruit. כסות לחה מחמת עצמן היכי משכחת לה? ksut
lacha machmat atzman heichi mishkachat lah? How do you get a moist
garment if it has its own moisture?
Same answer, ממרטא דביניתמי, mimarta deben itmi, the same way we said
this by little pieces of cloth we can say it by the
garment itself, it was made from wool that was coming from the
thigh area of the sheep and therefore was always moist. Anyway, that's
just the גמרא's Gemara assumption that similar to the question that we
began with when we're talking about the sort of the twigs, whether
it's twigs of olives or as we see even twigs of the
sesame, exactly what is the line, how much heat does it have
to give off to be considered giving off heat? So the גמרא
Gemara does not come to a conclusion here regarding the issue of
moisture. Now we move on to the next משנה, Mishnah, which gets
to other area... continuing the thing about what can be used and
this as you'll see is basically was paralleled in the ברייתא baraita
we just quoted a minute ago. טומנין בכסות ובפירות בכנפי יונה ובנסורת
של חרשים, tomnin biksut uvefirot bechanfei yona uvinisoret shel charashim, you can
insulate in garments, in fruit, again רש"י Rashi says fruit here means
things like, you know, beans or whatever, small little things. ובכנפי יונה,
ubechanfei yona, which are feathers from a dove... wings aren't they? Yeah,
feathers of a dove. ובנסורת
של חרשים,
ubinisoret
shel charashim, or in the like wood shavings, the sawdust
of carpenters. ובנוערת של פשתן, ubinuoret shel pishtan, and in like the
remnants of flax all these דקה, daka, as long as it's small
אפילו דקה, afilu daka, excuse me, even if it's small, these like
the remnants from the flax. רבי יהודה אוסר בדקה, Rabi Yehuda oser
bedaka, רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda says no, if it's small it's not
okay ומתיר בגסה, umatir begasa, he allows like large ones but not
small remnants. Apparently he feels that the small remnants somehow add heat,
I'm not exactly clear to me how. Let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. אמר רבי ינאי, amar Rabi Yannai, so now coming totally
from left field, תפילין צריכין גוף נקי כאלישע בעל כנפיים, tefillin tzrichin
guf naki ke-Elisha baal knafayim, when you wear your תפילין tefillin you
have to have a clean body like אלישע Elisha the owner of
wings. master of wings or feathers. So obviously you're seeing the tie-in
here. כנפי יונה, Kanfei yonah, בעל כנפיים. Ba'al Knafayim. So let's take
a look. מאי היא? Mai hi? What is this? How, what does
it mean that your body has to be clean? So אביי Abbayei
אמר amar שלא shelo יפיח yafiah בהן. bahen. You have to make
sure not to pass gas when you're wearing תפילין. tefillin. רבא Rava
אמר amar שלא shelo יישן yishan בהן. bahen. You have to make
sure you don't fall asleep because if you fall asleep, then you
will pass gas.
Okay, or you will, or just because sleep itself is considered to
be a הסח הדעת hesech hadaat and we have to be constantly
aware that you are wearing תפילין. tefillin. רש"י Rashi also says maybe
if you're a man maybe you'll have a seminal emission, תוספות Tosafot
says that we're not concerned about that, it would be a problem
but we're not concerned about that that that will happen. So now
there's an interesting debate between רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot to what
whether אביי Abbayei whether רבא Rava is being lenient or strict. רש"י
Rashi says that רבא Rava is being lenient. רבא Rava says I'm
normally not concerned that a person's going to pass gas, meaning or
people are able to control that. Okay, so you don't have to
be so concerned that that might happen. But what you do have
to be concerned about is that you might fall asleep. So that's
like, you know, it's like don't worry that, I mean you're not
allowed to pass gas when you're wearing תפילין, tefillin, but to say
I can't wear it because I'm afraid I might, I'm not so
concerned you might. Now that's a little strange because if anything you
would think it's more likely that you'll pass gas at any given
moment than you'll happen to fall asleep and not be able to
control it. So תוספות, Tosafot, you know, so תוספות Tosafot says that
no, רבא Rava is certainly concerned that you'll pass gas. He adds
to it an additional concern
that if you're like a little bit tired or whatever that you
also can't wear תפילין tefillin because you have to be concerned you
might nod off. So it's an additional concern in addition to that
of אביי. Abbayei. Both agree you can't pass gas or fall asleep
when wearing תפילין. tefillin. The question is how much you have to
say I'm afraid this might happen, I'm not going to wear תפילין.
tefillin. So אביי Abbayei just says only if you're afraid you'll pass
gas. I'm not afraid you'll fall asleep even if you're tired. And
רבא Rava says no, if you're tired, don't put on תפילין, tefillin,
you might fall asleep.
So meaning if you're waking up with somewhat of a stomachache then
according to— yeah,
that actually— then
you would be allowed to put on תפילין tefillin because I'm not
concerned you're going to pass?
According to the way רש"י Rashi reads it? Yeah, it's a funny
read of רש"י. Rashi. I don't really understand רש"י Rashi so well.
Yes.
But every guy I see at 6:00 AM in מנין minyan is
putting on תפילין. tefillin. I can't believe that none of them are
tired.
Yeah, it might be a little different if you're tired in the
process of waking up or if you're tired late in the day
and, you know, in the process of falling asleep. But, you know,
so anyway, these are certain הלכה halacha about תפילין. tefillin. Now I
do want to mention, you know, let's finish the story and then
I do want to mention a very important תוספות Tosafot about this.
So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says ואמאי v'amai
קרי kari ליה lei בעל כנפיים? Ba'al Knafayim? So why did it
mention אלישע Elisha and why is it calling him בעל כנפיים? Ba'al
Knafayim? What's the story with him? שפעם אחת shepa'am achat גזרה gazra
מלכות malchut רומי Romi הרשעה ha-resha'ah גזרה gezerah ישראל. Yisrael.
One time the evil Roman kingdom made a edict against the Jews.
שכל shekol המניח hamaniach תפילין tefillin ינקרו yenakru את et מוחו. mocho.
Anybody that wears תפילין tefillin his skull will be pierced, literally his
brains will be pierced. Obviously representing the תפילין של ראש Tefillin shel
Rosh because that's the most obvious place where you wear תפילין. tefillin.
והיה vehaya אלישע Elisha מניחם manicham
and this אלישע Elisha would wear them. ויצא veyatza לשוק lashuk not
only in private, he would go out in public in order to,
you know, publicly defy the edict of Rome and, you know, also
maybe be a model for his fellow Jews not to give in.
ראהו ra'ahu קסדור אחד kasdor echad so a certain officer saw him.
What does it say is the Greek there for קסדור?
kasdor Latin, it's from 'quaestor'. Quaestor, right. For a Roman, right, right,
right.
I remember that when I took the whatever, ancient studies. Quaestor. Anyway,
רש"י Rashi has an interesting thing for קסדור. kasdor? רש"י Rashi says
minstrel.
But I assume it doesn't mean the guy with the where the
with the maybe I don't know. Anyway, so this certain soldier saw
him. קסדור kasdor. אחד echad רץ מפניו ratz mipanav so he ran
away from him. ורץ אחריו veratz acharav so this Roman officer ran
after him. וכיון שהגיע אצלו vechevan shehigia etzlo so once the Roman
officer caught up with him, נטלם מראשו netalam merosho ואחזם בידו. va'achazam
beyado. He grabbed them off his head and he held them in
a hand. אמר לו amar lo מה זה בידך? mah zeh beyadecha?
What are you holding in your hand? אמר לו amar lo כנפי
יונה הן. kanfei yonah hen. He said to him, it's just feathers
of a dove. פשט את ידו pashat et yado he opened his
hand ונמצאו כנפי יונה. venimtzu kanfei yonah. Look at that, they had
turned into, it's like a magic trick, right? It just becomes feathers,
it turned into feathers of a dove. A miracle happened. לפיכך lefichach
קורין אותו korin oto אלישע בעל כנפיים. Elisha Ba'al Knafayim. That's why
he is given this name of אלישע בעל כנפיים. Elisha Ba'al Knafayim.
Now it doesn't speak about how careful he was בגוף נקי beguf
naki but presumably if you are so, you know, מקפיד makpid on
the מצווה mitzvah of תפילין tefillin and you're going to do it
in the face of the threat of death, we can assume that
he was seen as a model of what it means to care
deeply about תפילין, tefillin, so as the model of wearing תפילין בגוף
נקי. tefillin beguf naki. One minute. So ומאי שנא umai shena כנפי
יונה kanfei yonah משאר עופות? mish'ar ofot? Why did he pick a
dove's wings, a dove's feathers? Why did he mention a dove of
all things? משום דדמיא mishum didmiya כנסת ישראל Knesset Yisrael ליונה leyonah
because the congregation of Israel is compared to a dove. שנאמר shene'emar
כנפי יונה נחפה בכסף, kanfei yonah nechpa vakesef, like a bird's feathers,
like the feathers of a dove covered in silver. So what's the
significance of that comparison? מה יונה כנפיה מגינות עליה mah yonah knafeyah
meginot aleiha the same way a dove its feathers protect it, אף
ישראל מצוות מגינות עליהן af Yisrael mitzvot meginot aleihen even Israel mitzvot
protect them. So, its feathers protect it. Now, how do feathers of
a dove protect it more than the feathers of another bird? So
רש"י Rashi says כנפי יונה, kanfei yonah, רש"י Rashi says כמפרש לקמיה
kimfareish lekamei מפני שהן מצוות והן מגינות לישראל. mipnei shehein mitzvot vehein
meginot leyisrael. And how are they ככנפיים ליונה? keknafayim leyona?
I’m sorry, the next רש"י. Rashi. כנפיה מגינות עליה knafeha meginot aleha
מן הצינה, min hatzinah,
first of all, it keeps it warm. Okay, presumably other birds as
well. ומכל עוף ואדם הבא עליה היא נלחמת ומכה בראש גפה, umikol
of ve'adam haba aleha hi nilchemet umaka berosh gapah, people that try
to attack it, they wind up hitting its wings, מה שאין כן
בשאר עופות, ma she'ein kein bish'ar ofot, or she hits them with
its wings. If you try to attack it, it’ll hit you with
its
wings, מה שאין כן בשאר עופות. ma she'ein kein bish'ar ofot. Is
that really true? It's not true by other birds, that they don't
attack with their wings? So תוספות Tosafot has a different explanation. If
you look at תוספות Tosafot כנפיה מגינות עליה, knafeha meginot aleha, תוספות
Tosafot אומר ר"י דאמרינן במדרש omer ri de'amrinan bemidrash כל עוף כשהן
יגיעים נינוחים על גבי סלע. kol of keshehein yegi'im ninochim al gabei
sela.
Other birds just rest on a rock when they’re tired. והיונה בשעה
שיגעה פורחת באחת ונינוחת באחת. vehayona besha'a sheyage'a porachat be'achat veninochat be'achat.
And a dove when it’s tired, rests on one of its wings
but the other wing it sort of keeps on flapping and keeps
somewhat hovering. So again, I don't know if that's true, but that
somehow it uses its wings to protect itself in the process of
when it’s resting. So anyway, that’s why you have the כנפי יונה.
kanfei yonah. Now תוספות, Tosafot, get to your question in a minute,
תוספות, Tosafot, very important תוספות, Tosafot, at least for historical interest. תוספות
Tosafot says כאלישע בעל כנפיים. ke'elisha ba'al knafayim. If you look at
this תוספות, Tosafot, he says ואחי נחית אלישע דמסר נפשיה אע"ג דנפקא
לן מגוף נקי. v'hachi nachit elisha dimasir nafshia af al gav d'nafka
lan miguf naki. ומזה הטעם. umizeh hata'am.
Do you see this five lines down in the תוספות Tosafot כאלישע?
ke'elisha? Because of this reason of גוף נקי, guf naki, אין אנו
יכולים
להיפטר. ein anu yecholim lehipater. We can't say we don't have to
wear תפילין tfillin because we can't keep our body clean. Famous תוספות
Tosafot like we’re looking to exempt ourselves from תפילין, tfillin, but let's
keep on reading. שהרי בזה אנו יכולים להיזהר. sheharei bezeh anu yecholim
lehizaher. You can't use that as an excuse. You can keep yourself
from passing gas. ואין לתמוה על מה שמצווה זו רפויה בידינו. ve'ein
litmo'ah al mah shemitzvah zo refuya beyadeinu.
So you shouldn't be astounded that this מצווה mitzvah is very weak
in our hands. So what’s clear is תוספות Tosafot is dealing with
a phenomenon where even in Ashkenazi Jewry, where people were very, very
פרום, frum, they still were not so מקפיד makpid on תפילין. tfillin.
And we actually have this evidence from other ראשונים Rishonim at the
time of תוספות Tosafot that the things we consider like the most
basic, like תפילין tfillin and מזוזה, mezuzah, were things that had a
little bit fallen by the wayside. So תוספות Tosafot is trying to
defend it, maybe it’s because we think we can’t keep a גוף
נקי. guf naki. He says that's really not a good explanation. That
obviously that we could do. So then why are we not so
careful to wear תפילין? tfillin? So he says שגם בימי חכמים הייתה
רפויה כדתניא בפרק רבי אליעזר דמילה. shegam bimei chachamim hayta refuya kedetanya
beperek rabi eliezer demila. וכן הוא אומר כל מצווה שלא מסרו עצמן
ישראל עליה בשעת גזירת המלכות כגון תפילין עדיין היא רפויה בידיהם. vechein
hu omer kol mitzvah shelo masru atzman yisrael aleha bish'at gezeirat hamalchut
kegon tfillin adayin hi refuya beyadeihem. Look, we see אלישע Elisha was
the only one who was standing up to defend תפילין. tfillin. The
rest of the Jewish people did not. So because we did not
sort of defend it when it was being attacked, that creates some
metaphysical reality or some precedent and it leads to us not being
so מקפיד. makpid. So it’s quite interesting because תוספות Tosafot usually tries
to reconcile practice with the גמרא. Gemara. But here, he’s not letting
it go, meaning he’s giving people like don’t feel maybe overly guilty,
like we’re not the first or the last that’s not going to
be great with תפילין. tfillin. But at the other hand, he doesn't
want to reconcile that and say it’s okay. He actually says really
you gotta be wearing
תפילין. tfillin. So it’s quite an interesting balance of not overly criticizing
the reality, but again against other types of תוספות Tosafot normal תוספות
Tosafot approach, not saying that it’s okay. First Michael and then Joe.
But this brings up some other larger questions. So this is a
guy who is openly flouting the decree, I mean what he could
have done is put them on in his home, say קריאת שמע
ושמונה עשרה. Kriat Shema u'Shmona Esrei. Right, right. So the question over
here is when should we be openly flouting a decree? And then
what's our responsibility, let's say, to put more people in danger, or
ourselves in danger.
Right. So that raises a good question which I'm not going to
answer. I mean that's a much more of a סנהדרין Sanhedrin question,
although this is an application of it, about like יהרג ואל יעבור.
yehareig ve'al ya'avor. Now this is, of course it seems like it’s
a שעת השמד sha'at hashmad that the government is trying to it’s
not just a simple thing of not doing a מצווה mitzvah at
one time, they're trying to outlaw מצווה mitzvah and actually clamp down
on Jewish observance. So therefore it would still be יהרג ואל יעבור.
yehareig ve'al ya'avor. But it does raise a good question about open
defiance versus private and to what degree is there an idea of
setting an, maybe willing to overly martyr yourself in order to set
an example for other people. I’ll read you by the way one
line from the next תוספות Tosafot נחמני ראשו. nachmani rosho. תוספות Tosafot
has a problem. What's תוספות's Tosafot problem? ואף על גב דאמרינן בסנהדרין
בשעת גזירת המלכות. ve'af al gav de'amrinan besanhedrin bish'at gezeirat hamalchut. The
first wide line, נחמני ראשו, nachmani rosho, now I’m on the second
wide line, אפילו אמצווה קלה יהרג ואל יעבור ואפילו שינוי ערקתא דמסאנא.
afilu amitzvah kala yehareig ve'al ya'avor ve'afilu shinuy arketa demas'ana. So תוספות
Tosafot is bothered. This is a שעת השמד. sha'at hashmad. He’s not
bothered why he wore them, he’s bothered why he took them off!
Even if the soldier is running after you, you should keep on
wearing them.
נחמני ראשו, nachmani rosho, but here אבל הכא אינו עושה כלום אלא
שאין לו תפילין בראשו שעה אחת. aval hacha eino ose klum ela
she'ein lo tfillin berosho sha'a achat. You gotta take off your תפילין
tfillin sometime. So the soldier is running after me, oh I decided
now it’s time to take off my תפילין. tfillin. But the funny
thing about this תוספות Tosafot is, my reaction would have been like
my... like, you know, flouting
the edict and asking almost to get in trouble as opposed to
doing it in private. תוספות Tosafos is bothered with the opposite. What
do you do taking off your תפילין tefillin even if you're being
chased? Okay, so which by the way it's an interesting if you
combine the two תוספות, Tosafos, because one of the things we do
know about the period of ראשוני אשכנז, Rishonei Ashkenaz, period of תוספות,
Tosafos, was the degree to which the Jews were מוסר moser themselves,
martyrdom themselves, particularly in אשכנז Ashkenaz rather than convert to Christianity at
the time of the Crusades. So he like, you know, so his
approach to אלישע, Elisha, you should have even been more מוסר moser
yourself until he's, you know, reconciled, says. But by תפילין tefillin that
they weren't, that that is, that that's the people weren't so good
at. מסירות נפש mesirus nefesh they was, תפילין tefillin not. It's quite
a fascinating, you know, phenomenon. Yeah, Charlie, you had a question.
Well there's תוספות Tosafos that brings the question, why are, why are
we not wearing תפילין tefillin right this second?
Well, no, that's different, meaning we, the way we reconcile, thank you
for mentioning the גוף נקי guf naki issue, is it's clear in
the גמרא Gemara they would wear תפילין tefillin the whole day. What
the, you know, what the פוסקים poskim say is we who cannot
be so good at keeping גוף נקי, guf naki, we only wear
it בשעת תפילה b'shas tefilla and we hope that for that period
of time we'll be able to remain cognizant that the תפילין tefillin
is on us, not הסח הדעת, hesech hadaas, and also stop ourselves
from passing gas. But that's what, but it's certainly not the problem
that we don't do the מצווה mitzvah of תפילין, tefillin, right? תוספות
Tosafos is talking about a much bigger phenomenon that people largely didn't
wear it period. We're talking about that we basically, you know, we
just shorten the amount of time each day we wear it because
of these concerns. So that's exactly how we strike that balance. Yes.
So if we're going to wear it for, for תפילה, tefilla, why
don't we wear it by מנחה? mincha?
Again, it's the same type of a thing. You do it once
and like, and that's it for the day, exactly. That's the basic
way we've reconciled. Okay, yes.
That answered my question though. Was it basically just as a שעת
השמד?
sha'as hashmad? Well, whether that means that you should still go out
looking for trouble is still a different question. I agree that's an
important issue. Okay, so
ובנסורת של חרשים, u'v'nisores shel charashim, so now sawdust. איבעיא להו לרבי
יהודה אנסורת של חרשים קאי או אנעורת של פשתן קאי. Ibaya lehu
l'Rabbi Yehuda a'nisores shel charashim kai o a'neores shel pishtan kai. איבעיא
להו רבי יהודה אנסורת של חרשים קאי או אנעורת של פשתן קאי
Ibaya lehu Rabbi Yehuda a'nisores shel charashim kai o a'neores shel pishtan
kai when רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said thick but not, but you
can use but not small, not fine, is he talking about sawdust
או אנעורת של פשתן קאי, o a'neores shel pishtan kai, is he
talking about like the sort of remnants from the flax when you,
you know, comb the flax to make it into linen? So תא
שמע דתניא, ta shma d'tanya, we have a ברייתא, braisa, רבי יהודה
אומר נעורת של פשתן דקה הרי הוא כזבל. Rabbi Yehuda oimer neores
shel pishtan daka harei hu k'zevel. So he specifically talking about, he
about the flax and he says the combings of the flax if
it's small, if it's, if it's like fine as opposed to large,
coarse, then it is like זבל, zevel, it is like excrement which
means it's a problem, then it gives off heat. So he assumes
for some reason that these things will give off heat if you
have the fine grains of it. שמע מינה אנעורת של פשתן קאי,
shma mina a'neores shel pishtan kai, so we see he's talking about
the flax issue, שמע מינה. shma mina. That's good point. Okay. So
that was the issue of various things that are not a problem
with a little bit of a debate about the flax. Let's take
a look now at the next משנה. mishna. טומנין בשלחים, tomnin b'shlachim,
you can insulate with,
with strips of leather or this is even like hides, hides of
animals. ומטלטלין אותן, u'm'taltalin oisan, and you can,
and those aren't מוקצה. muktzeh. So you can actually move them whether
you they you've wrapped the pot in it or haven't wrapped the
pot in it. בגיזי צמר, bigizey tzemer, you can insulate with shearings
of wool, ואין מטלטלין אותן, v'ein m'taltalin oisan, but the shearings of
wool as we learned the other day are מוקצה. muktzeh. Normally you
use shearings of wool, you put them in your sewing kit, you
use them for things you can't do on שבת, Shabbos, so those
are מוקצה. muktzeh. So you can insulate but you can't move it.
It's מוקצה. muktzeh. So how do you get to your pot? That'll
be the next line. But as opposed to hides, hides you can
use even if you haven't made them into shoes or belts. You
can like, you know, lie on a hide, you know, like in
those like, you know, teepees or whatever, you know, you always have
them have a hide out there as a type of a carpet
or something. So a hide you can use, a hide isn't מוקצה,
muktzeh, but shearings of wool, those are מוקצה, muktzeh, but you can
use them to insulate.
Right, right, unless it's the stuffing that already came out. Anyway, כיצד
הוא עושה, keitzad hu oise, so what do you do? You've got
this insulated in shearings of wool. What are you going to do?
So נוטל את הכיסוי והן נופלות. notel es hakisui v'hein noflos. You
just lift up the cover of the pot and you scoop it
out while it's still in the insulation. And the wool falls off
incidentally. So that's טלטול מן הצד, tiltul min hatzad, you're not directly
moving the wool, you're moving the cover of the pot, the wool
is moving incidentally and you're doing it for the sake of the
pot. That's okay. So that's what you do. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה
אומר, Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya oimer, רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar
ben Azarya says
now by the way רש"י Rashi has an interesting question. Why can
you move the cover of the pot? Why isn't the cover of
the pot a בסיס? basis? If the wool's on top of the
cover, so the cover is a בסיס basis to the wool. So
רש"י Rashi says no, because the wool is just there to cover
the pot. What does that mean? So I think what רש"י Rashi
means is a בסיס basis normally supports, is there to support the
thing that is on it. This is there for the sake of
the thing below, not the thing below is there for the thing
on top. Let's say you put, you know, like a, you know,
cover on top on a type of a thing. You wouldn't call
the thing a בסיס basis for the cover, the cover is a
covering for the thing below. So therefore because there it does not
change the status of the cover of the pot and that is
not מוקצה. muktzeh. One minute. So that's what the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma says. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה אומר קופה מטה על צדה ונוטל
שמא יטול ואינו יכול להחזיר. Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya oimer kuppa mata
al tzida v'notel shema yitol v'eino yachol l'hachzir. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה
אומר קופה מטה על צדה ונוטל שמא יטול ואינו יכול להחזיר. Rabbi
Elazar ben Azaryah omer kuppah matteh al tzidah venotel shema yitol ve'eino
yakhol lehakhzir. If you've got this pot in a box and the
box is filled with these sheep shearings, these wool shearings, which are
מוקצה, muktzah, what you do is tip the box over and get
the pot to come out, hopefully without spilling its contents, okay, because
I'm afraid that if you take the pot out, you won't be
able to put it back in. Why? Because then the sort of
hole that is made, the shape that is formed in this thing
for the pot, as soon as you take the pot out, the
wool will fall over and fill it up, and you won't be
able to put it back in. Why not? A מוקצה muktzah problem,
some other problem, we'll see in the גמרא. Gemara. וחכמים אומרים נוטל
ומחזיר. Vechakhamim omrim notel umakhzir. We're not concerned. You take the pot
out and then you'll put it back in. So he somehow is
worried that hole will get filled. We'll see what the concern is
in the time of the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, we'll have to see
what the problem is. Oh, yes, אריה? Aryeh?
I thought it has to be completely surrounding the entire. It does.
But here it's only covering the top.
No, it's covering the sides and the top.
So how are you going to move it without touching it?
Well, I think in the first case, you picked up the cover
and then you scooped it out, whereas now it's still sitting in
the insulation. You've got your thing in insulation, you remove the cover.
But does the cover also become.
Yeah, but you grab onto the handle of the cover. Handles. Pull
it off and the stuff falls off of the handle cover and
you scoop it out. Okay?
Alright. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. So גמרא
Gemara says,
יתיב רבי יונתן בן עכנאי ורבי יונתן בן אלעזר. Yativ Rabbi Yonatan
ben Akhnai veRabbi Yonatan ben Elazar. Two רבי יונתןs Rabbi Yonatan were
sitting, בן עכנאי ורבי יונתן בן אלעזר. ben Akhnai veRabbi Yonatan ben
Elazar. ויתיב רבי חנינא בר חמא גבייהו. Veyativ Rabbi Chanina bar Chama
gavaihu. And רבי חנינא בר חמא Rabbi Chanina bar Chama were sitting
with them. וקמיבעיא להו. Vekamibaia lehu. He asked them. שלחים של
בעל הבית תנן? Shlachim shel ba'al habayit tenan? When we say it's
just like repeating type of a theme here, what exact type of
twigs? What exact type of wool? What exact type of etcetera. So,
what exact type of hide? Is it hides that are owned by
a בעל הבית, ba'al habayit, like a homeowner, a personal
privately owned hide?
אבל של אומן? Aval shel uman? But if it's of a craftsperson,
it's actually of the leather maker? כיון דקפיד עלייהו לא מטלטלינן להו.
Keivan dekhapid alaihu lo metalpelinan lehu. If he has hides in his
store, he's not going to want to use them for any other
purpose because they'll get dirty and he has to cut them up
and sell them and he wants to keep them clean. So maybe
those are מוקצה muktzah because
off-limits until he cuts them up. או דילמא, O dilma, is that
what we say, ולא מטלטלינן להו? velo metalpelinan lehu? או דילמא אפילו
של אומן תנן? O dilma afilu shel uman tenan? Even that of
a craftsperson, you know, even he's willing to use his hides and
even if he's going to later cut them up and use them
for some other purpose, or process them. וכל שכן של בעל הבית
Vekhol sheken shel ba'al habayit and certainly a בעל הבית ba'al habayit
is not מוקצה. muktzah. אמר להו רבי יונתן בן אלעזר. Amar lehu
Rabbi Yonatan ben Elazar. רבי יונתן בן אלעזר Rabbi Yonatan ben Elazar
said, מסתברא של בעל הבית תנן. Mistavra shel ba'al habayit tenan. It's
quite interesting by the way, it's אמר להו אמר להו, amar lehu
amar lehu, there's three people but they're all talking to one another,
right? It's not like he said back to the person who asked.
He said to the other two. So they're having like a group
conversation. אמר להו רבי יונתן בן אלעזר מסתברא של בעל הבית תנן.
Amar lehu Rabbi Yonatan ben Elazar mistavra shel ba'al habayit tenan. Makes
sense that we're talking about only of a homeowner's. אבל של אומן,
Aval shel uman, but if it belongs to the actual craftsperson, קפיד
עלייהו, kapid alaihu, those are מוקצה, muktzah, he doesn't want anybody using
them. אמר להו רבי חנינא בר חמא. Amar lehu Rabbi Chanina bar
Chama. רבי חנינא בר חמא Rabbi Chanina bar Chama said back to
the two of them, כך אמר רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי. Kakh amar
Rabbi Yishmael barbi Yosei. This is what רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי Rabbi
Yishmael barbi Yosei says.
אבא, Abba, my father,
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosei, שלחא הוה. shalkha havah. He was a hides
person, he was like a leather worker. Okay, tanner. Thank you. ואמר,
Ve'amar, שלחא shalkha actually refers to the hide itself, but yes, he
was a tanner. ואמר, Ve'amar, he would say, הביאו שלחים ונשב עליהם
Hevi'u shlachim venishev aleihem and he would say, bring me hides and
let's sit, bring me those hides from my storeroom and let's sit
on them. רש"י Rashi says it was during the week, תוספות Tosafot
says it was even on שבת, Shabbat, but either way, the point
is, is that it's very clear he had no problem using his
hides, his stored hides that he was eventually going to process and
sell. He had no problem using them when he needed a hide
to sit on.
And the point is, yes, to make a modern corollary, you wouldn't
according to the first opinion you wouldn't be allowed to use like
the nice towel in the bathroom that you might want to use
just for the guests because you don't want it to get so
dirty, right?
It's an interesting question.
Right, so look every single time this comes up the גמרא Gemara
asks the question, exactly this, exactly that. So it's hard to sort
of extrapolate, you know, what is the degree of הקפדה, hakpadah, how
much.
Again, I think that the point is that if somebody came you'd
have a reason to use it, that would be that would certainly
not be considered to be מוקצה. muktzah. You know, so if you
were had some guest came right now on שבת Shabbat you would
use it on שבת Shabbat or whatever. I don't think that would
be a problem. I think if what do you call it, I
think this is an issue where there is you would never use
it on שבת, Shabbat, that was the concern because you were going
to use it in
your professionally to make leather items out of it. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like
this. מיתיבי. Meitivei. נסרים של בעל הבית. Nesarin shel ba'al habayit. So
here the גמרא Gemara assumes that maybe things are the same like
Michael wants to generalize. So it says if you have planks, you
know of wood. So if you're a homeowner, מטלטלין אותן. metalpelin otan.
You can move them because you know maybe you'll want to make
a table out of a plank or you'll want to sit on
a plank. By the way, if they have dirt. floors you understand
better why you're interested in getting high or some type of thing
to sit on. Okay anyway, ושל אומן אין מטלטלין אותן, v'shel uman
ain metaltlin osan, but if they're if they're owned by a carpenter,
you can't move it because he doesn't want people sitting on his
planks of wood, he's got to, you know, do something with it,
he's got to cut it up and, you know, build it into
the building, he doesn't want it to get ruined. So ואי חשב
למישב עליהם פסקא לאורחין, v'ee chashev l'meishav aleihem paska l'orchin, and this
is I think David asked this question the other day, people have
been asking: when can you make something מוקצה muktzah non-מוקצה? muktzah? Is
thinking about what you're planning to do enough? Do you have to
actually use them? So it might depend on the item, but here
we're saying we're thinking is enough. If you thought and you planned
to use it even if you're a carpenter and you said when
שבת Shabbos comes, you know what I'm going to do, I'm going
to put it on these two, you know, on these two
post—not post or whatever, you know, mounds. I can't think right now.
Anyway, and we'll use it as a little table. So, and you
thought about that before שבת. Shabbat. You were planning on using it
before שבת. Shabbat. So in that case, בין כך ובין כך מטלטלין,
bein kach u'vein kach metaltlin, then you can, then you can use
it because then you've made it not מוקצה. muktzah. So what do
you see though? The general assumption is without special designation that this
thing that's set aside for business use for is considered מוקצה. muktzah.
So if that's true about planks, that it's—it should be true about
the skins. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, שאני נסרי דקפיד עלייהו.
shani nisarei d'kapeid aleihu. No, planks are different. Planks you are מקפיד
makpid on, skins you're not. That explains to us the difference. But
it says you can't generalize, right? So people might not have a
problem sitting on skins. Who knows, maybe the process of tanning them
and processing them, even if they get a little dirty, you know,
skins can't get too damaged. You know, maybe planks can get more
damaged. So you can't generalize, so skins even if you're going to
use them as, you know, in your, you know, as if for
processing and for business purposes, you're not מקפיד makpid whereas planks of
wood you are. תא שמע, Ta shema, let's try again.
עורות, oros, if you have skins, בין עבודים בין שאין עבודים, bein
avudim bein she'ein avudim, whether they've been tanned or not tanned, whether
they're raw skins or they've been actually treated and turned into leather,
מותר לטלטלם בשבת, mutar l'taltalam b'Shabbat, you can move them on שבת
Shabbat because you have a use, right? You can sit on them
as we've seen. לא אמרו עבודים lo amru avudim when we see
that the rabbis say that there's a difference between whether they've been
tanned and processed and turned into leather or not, that's not for
שבת Shabbat purposes. For שבת Shabbat purposes, even without that, you can
use them, it's a mat, it's not מוקצה. muktzah. So when did
חז"ל Chazal care about עבודים avudim that it makes a difference that
they were processed? אלא לעניין טומאה בלבד, ela l'inyan tumah bilvad, only
for the purposes of טומאה. tumah. It's not considered able to become
טמא tamei until it's processed, but it is—it is not a מוקצה
muktzah concern. Now this might seem like a trivial point, but I
want to stop for a minute and mention something because תוספות Tosafot
brings it up. In a later גמרא Gemara that talks about מוקצה,
muktzah, I mean we won't get to it for a little while,
but anyway, it brings in a lot of discussions of טומאה וטהרה
tumah v'taharah and whether something is considered a vessel, a כלי kli
to become טמא tamei will have a—determine whether it is considered a
vessel and therefore not מוקצה, muktzah, right? So the גמרא Gemara brings
in like if it's not yet finished enough to be considered a
vessel to become טמא, tamei, then it's not yet finished enough to
be considered a vessel to be considered something you would use and
therefore it's considered מוקצה. muktzah. And it assumes that there's an equation
between these two categories. So תוספות Tosafot says, so why here are
they unequal categories? Here it says that even if it's not processed
or tanned, it's not מוקצה, muktzah, even though it can't become טמא.
tamei. So here they're unequal categories. So רש"י Rashi seems to indicate
that it's like a גזירת הכתוב. gezeiras hakasuv. רש"י Rashi just says,
no, there's a special הלכה halacha that leather doesn't become טמא tamei
until it's tanned. And therefore it's not because it's not a vessel,
it's not because it's not usable, it's just a special, you know,
criteria for טומאה—criterion. tumah תוספות Tosafot disagrees. He says leather can become
טמא tamei even if it's not tanned if you designate it that
to be to use. And תוספות Tosafot says here's the difference. The
difference is whether it
requires—if something can be a vessel as long as you intend for
it, then it is not מוקצה. muktzah. Meaning תוספות Tosafot says untanned
leather is not טמא, tamei, cannot become טמא tamei because it's not
yet normally at the stage where you would use it. But if
you actually thought I'm going to use this untanned leather, then it
actually would be able to become טמא. tamei. So physically it's complete
enough. It's just that normally people don't use it and therefore it's
not going to become טמא. tamei. But if you've decided you want
to use it, then it will be able to become טמא. tamei.
So תוספות Tosafot says when do we look at the category of
טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah to say something isn't a vessel and therefore
is מוקצה muktzah is only if it is so incomplete that even
if you wanted to use it, it would not be טמא. tamei.
Therefore that's complete—that's so incomplete and so unusable that therefore it's also
going to be מוקצה. muktzah. But something like leather actually, since it
has the potential of becoming טמא tamei even though it requires special
designation, therefore not. And probably I've lost people, I'm sorry if I
did, but I just wanted to make the point that the גמרא
Gemara is—is saying there's a difference between the category of מוקצה muktzah
and טומאה. tumah. And תוספות Tosafot actually says there's a lot of—there's
a whole גמרות Gemaros that compare the two cases, but this—so there
you go. you have to understand that this is a slightly an
exception to that rule. Okay, but that's what we've said. We've said
that these untanned leathers are not טמא, tamei, but they are, but
they also are not מוקצה. Muktzeh. And now the גמרא Gemara says
like this, so מאי לאו, mai lav, is it not, לא שנא
שבבעל הבית ולא שנא של אומן, lo shna she-ba'al ha-bayit ve-lo shna
shel uman, that regardless of whether they're owned by a homeowner or
by a craftsman, it says that they are not מוקצה? Muktzeh? So
you see that this brings, this proves our point. So the גמרא
Gemara says, לא, lo, no, שבבעל הבית, she-ba'al ha-bayit, we're only talking
about if they're owned by a homeowner. אבל של אומן, aval shel
uman, so the גמרא Gemara says אבל של אומן מאי? aval shel
uman mai? So what you gonna say? That leather owned by a
craftsperson אין מטלטלין, ein metaltelin, it is מוקצה? Muktzeh? אי הכי, i
hachi, so if that's true, הא דתניא, ha d'tanya, the ברייתא Baraita
moves on to say there's cases that make a difference, ולא אמרו
עבודים לענין טומאה בלבד, v'lo amru avudim l'inyan tum'ah bilvad, that when
does it matter that they're processed or tanned, only for purposes of
טומאה? tumah? Why, if it's looking to make a distinction, did it
run to the טומאה tumah category? לפלוג ולתני בדידיה, liflog v'lisni b'didei,
you should have made a more important distinction since you're already talking
about מוקצה. Muktzeh. במה דברים אמורים, ba-meh devarim amurim, when are they
not מוקצה? Muktzeh? שבבעל הבית, she-ba'al ha-bayit, if they're homeowner, if they're
owned by a homeowner. אבל של אומן, aval shel uman, if they're
owned by a craftsman, לא, lo, then it's, then it is מוקצה.
Muktzeh. Okay, so if you're looking to make a distinction and there
is a distinction, leathers owned by a craftsman, why do you run
to discuss טומאה tumah cases? Just point out that there's a מוקצה
Muktzeh distinction. So the גמרא Gemara says כולהו דבעל הבית קא מיירי.
kulu d'ba'al ha-bayit ka-mari. No, because we want to talk about leathers
owned by a בעל הבית. ba'al ha-bayit. We don't want to talk
about craftsmen. We want to talk about the normal בעל הבית ba'al
ha-bayit leathers. So for his leathers, the distinction is, for מוקצה Muktzeh
it's never מוקצה. Muktzeh. For טומאה, tumah, it matters whether they've been
processed or not. Okay, כתנאי, k'tanna'ei, let's say this is a debate
of תנאים. Tanna'im. This is a debate of תנאים. Tanna'im. עורות שבבעל
הבית מטלטלין אותן, orot she-ba'al ha-bayit metaltelin otan, you can move the
leathers of a homeowner, אבל לא של אומן, aval lo shel uman,
not of a craftsperson, ובשל אומן אין מטלטלין אותן. u-veshel uman ein
metaltelin otan. רבי יוסי אומר אחד זה ואחד זה מטלטלין אותן, Rabbi
Yossi omer echad zeh v'echad zeh metaltelin otan, whether a craftsperson or
an expert, excuse me, whether a homeowner or a craftsperson, you can
move the leathers, they are not מוקצה. Muktzeh. Now I will remind
you that remember who said that his father was a tanner and
would move the and would sit on his skin? רבי ישמעאל ברבי
יוסי. Rabbi Yishmael b'Rebbi Yossi. So רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, the son
of רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, said his father was a tanner. רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi was a tanner and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi would
sit on skins even though they would be in the, you know,
in the storehouse to be used professionally. And here רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi is saying you can even a craftsperson can move those skins
on שבת. Shabbat. Yes, these are you're not מקפיד, makpid, you are
willing to sit on them. Yes, that's רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yossi point.
So it actually works out very nicely there. Okay, so this is
a question about how much is something again מוקצה Muktzeh if it's
something in theory you could use, but maybe you set it aside,
maybe you don't want to because it might get ruined and so
on and as I said that there is an interesting distinction here
that something might not be able to become טמא, tamei, it's not
and it's not enough of a vessel to be able to become
טמא, tamei, but it's enough usable, enough of a vessel to be
not מוקצה Muktzeh and that's an issue that the גמרא Gemara will
get into later. Yes, Charlie?
Regarding special case of leather, there's the leather that they gets tanned
to produce sofas, and there's leather that gets preserved to produce קלף
klaf that we use for writing סת"ם.
stam. So I don't know which we're talking about. I assume the
former, but
I would assume the former, but if it's talking about the former
then there's a question of is קלף klaf always מוקצה? Muktzeh?
Well, we had the case as we had little swatches of cloth
that were...
No, the קלף klaf like being the what we write סת"ם stam
on.
קלף, klaf, so actually it's an interesting question. Blank paper and pens
and pencils, what is their status? So some people treat them as
completely מוקצה Muktzeh like עצים ואבנים. etzim va-avanim. I've always assumed and
then I've found that I think the שמירת שבת Shemirat Shabbat says
the same thing that they're like a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור. kli she-melachto
l'issur. They're still a כלי, kli, right? Just a כלי kli you
normally do something prohibited on שבת, Shabbat, writing with them. So what's
the story about a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור? kli she-melachto l'issur? You can
move it לצורך מקומו l'tzorech mekomo or you know לצורך עצמו, l'tzorech
atzmo, but you can't move it like to protect it. So if
you let's say sometimes I don't know you need something to pry
something, can you grab a pen on שבת Shabbat to pry a
pen open, you know a lid open? So yes you can.
Okay fine.
So looking at what the גמרא Gemara is doing is though, you
know just how does it relate this back to the משכן Mishkan
because...
Well you know what? That's a perfect segue. So let's take a
look at the next discussion. I'm serious. So now in the middle
of nothing, not in nothing, in the middle of not the context
we would have expected, in the middle of a whole discussion here
about insulating and מוקצה, Muktzeh, we have a like the foundational discussion
about the ל"ט מלאכות lamed tet melachot and let's take a look
even though we're going to be formally introduced to it only about
25 דפים daphim from here. Right. The אהל, ohel, which we had
at the... Well fine fine. הרי יתיב וקא מיבעי להו. harei yativ
v'ka mibay'lu. So this same group, the two רבי יונתןs Rabbi Yonathan
and who other רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba was
it? רבי חנינא בר חמא Rabbi Chanina bar Chama were sitting and
they were having and they were raising the following question. They moved
after they finished discussing leathers of a craftsperson and leathers of a
homeowner, they raised this question. הא דתנן, had d'tnan, that's what we're
going to see about 25 דף, daf, 24 דף daf from now.
אבות מלאכות ארבעים חסר אחת, Avos melachos arba'im chaser achas, that there
are thirty-nine categories of מלאכה. melacha. So כנגד מי? keneged mi? What
do they correspond to? Now sometimes כנגד מי keneged mi can mean
just like, you know, like some type of a midrashic type of
symbolism. But here it seems like the question much more specifically was,
where do we get the idea of thirty-nine מלאכות melachos from? Pretty
important question. So let's take a look. אמר ליה רבי חנינא בר
חמא, Amar lei Rabbi Chanina bar Chama, רבי חנינא בר חמא Rabbi
Chanina bar Chama said to them, כנגד עבודת המשכן, keneged avodas hamishkan,
the workings in the המשכן. mishkan. So which presumably means we get
them from what they did to build the המשכן. mishkan. אמר ליה
רבי יונתן בן רבי אלעזר, Amar lei Rabbi Yonatan ben Rabbi Elazar,
so רבי יונתן בן רבי אלעזר Rabbi Yonatan ben Rabbi Elazar said,
כך אמר רבי שמעון בן רבי יוסי, kach amar Rabbi Shimon ben
Rabbi Yossi, again it's interesting, רבי יונתן בן רבי אלעזר Rabbi Yonatan
ben Rabbi Elazar quoting רבי שמעון בן רבי יוסי, Rabbi Shimon ben
Rabbi Yossi, same way he quoted him before about leather, here he's
quoting him about this issue. רבי שמעון בן רבי יוסי בן לקוניא,
Rabbi Shimon ben Rabbi Yossi ben Lakunya, כנגד, keneged, so maybe so
כנגד מלאכה מלאכתו ומלאכת שבתורה ארבעים חסר אחת. keneged melacha melachto umelachet
shebatorah arba'im chaser achas. The number of times it says the word
מלאכה melacha in the תורה, Torah, מלאכה, melacha, מלאכתו, melachto, מלאכת, melachet,
if we count all those times you'll get to thirty-nine. Okay, where
I will talk about. בעי רבי יוסי, Ba'ei Rabbi Yossi, so רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi asked, ויבא הביתה לעשות מלאכתו, vayavo habayta la'asos melachto,
that פסוק pasuk by יוסף, Yosef, he came to the house to
do his business. ממניינו הוא או לא? miminyano hu o lo? Is
that counted in the thirty-nine or not? Because presumably they had forty,
but they knew they had to eliminate one. So they're trying to
identify which one they have to eliminate. So is that counted or
not? אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said, וליתי
ספר תורה ולימני. velisei sefer Torah velimnei. I don't get it. Why
don't we just count how many מלאכתוs melachto we have and you'll
see is this one count, is this extra or not extra?
מי לא אמר רבה
בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן,
Mi lo amar Rabbah
bar
bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, did רבה בר בר חנה Rabbah bar
bar Chana not say, אמר רבי
יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan, לא זזו
משם עד שהביאו ספר תורה ומנאום, lo zazu misham ad sheheviu sefer
Torah umina'um, that in another scenario they when they had a question
like this they actually took out a ספר תורה sefer Torah and
counted. So רש"י Rashi doesn't know the exact context, but he thinks
he thinks it's about the question about what is the middle letter
of the תורה. Torah. You know, we say it's the ו vav
of גחון. gachon. Right. So anyway, so the גמרא Gemara discusses has
a whole discussion about can we really know it and maybe we
don't have this we're not we don't have a precise ספר תורה
sefer Torah in terms of the extra extra letters or missing letters.
Anyway, so רש"י Rashi said in the context of that discussion they
took out a ספר תורה sefer Torah and they counted. So here
too let's take out a ספר תורה sefer Torah and count and
see how many times it says מלאכה. melacha. אמר ליה, Amar lei,
כי קא מספקא לי הנהו. ki ka mesapka li hanhu. Here's why
I have a question. It's presumably I did count, I know there
are forty, I know there's one extra, and here's my question. משום
דכתיב, mishum dechtiv, we got another פסוק, pasuk, והמלאכה הייתה דים, vehamelacha
haysah dayam, and the the work or the job, you know, the
the the task was sufficient. Yeah, what you know, when they were
collecting all of the material for the משכן mishkan and they had
more than they needed. ממניינו הוא? Miminyano hu? Do you count that?
And that gets and that and that gets you your thirty-nine? So
you eliminate the פסוק pasuk by יוסף. Yosef. והא, Veha, and the
פסוק pasuk by יוסף, Yosef, how do we eliminate it? כמאן דאמר
לעשות צרכיו נכנס. keman d'amar la'asos tzrachav nichnas. So there's a question
how do we the פסוק pasuk יוסף Yosef went to the house
to do his work. Does to do his work mean literally to
do his tasks? You know, it's time to do his tasks, so
he's got to whatever, sweep the house or whatever יוסף Yosef would
do. Or is it a euphemism? It meant he meant to take
care of business, meaning he actually was going to give into אשת
פוטיפר. Eishes Potiphar. So if it meant he was going to give
into אשת פוטיפר, Eishes Potiphar, it doesn't mean tasks and work. So
then you would not count that. That you would eliminate the יוסף
Yosef פסוק pasuk and that's how you'd get
thirty-nine. והא והמלאכה הייתה דים, Veha vehamelacha haysah dayam, and therefore the
פסוק pasuk that says that the מלאכה melacha was enough when they
were doing the משכן, mishkan, when they were collecting the materials, הכי
קאמר, hachi ka'amar, this is what it means. דשלים ליה עבידתא, deshalim
lei avidta, all the work was finished for the משכן. mishkan. All
the sewing, all the knitting, all the dyeing, all the work was
done and therefore that פסוק pasuk counts.
So
do we say that or not? So the גמרא Gemara says תיקו.
teiku. We don't know. So now one minute, one minute. Did I
skip? I didn't skip. Okay. But there's no other side. So I'll
tell you the other side. The other side is that so here's
the way. The basic assumption is we've got forty מלאכות melachos that
it says in the תורה, Torah, we got to get rid of
one. So either we keep the one by the משכן, mishkan, makes
sense, it's by the משכן, mishkan, get rid of the one by
יוסף Yosef and say there it doesn't really mean work or task,
it just means take care of his business, it's a euphemism. Or
no, we say the יוסף Yosef actually was going to the house
to do his work and it means work and it's counted and
we eliminate the משכן mishkan one. Why would we eliminate the משכן
mishkan one? Because רש"י Rashi says פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk
isn't that the sort of the the work that they're doing, the
dyeing, the knitting, the whatever, that that was done. The פשט pshat
of the פסוק pasuk means all of the bringing was done, right
that they brought enough material. So that's not a normal מלאכה. melacha.
מלאכה melacha is like craft type of a work. That's more like
the job was done. So job doesn't mean the sort of the
work was done. Okay so that's the issue. You have to eliminate
one. Do you eliminate יוסף Yosef because it doesn't mean work, it
means taking care of business? Or do you eliminate the משכן mishkan
one because you say that that means the job was done, not
the work? And either way though we know we have to get
to thirty-nine. Now let me take a minute here to pause because
there's a... We are, you know what, I'm going to actually read,
yeah, no, let me actually, let me actually read one more פסוק
*Pasuk*, one more line, and then I want to really discuss the
issues that are raised here. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this. תניא כמאן דאמר כנגד keneged עבודת המשכן *Tanya keman d'amar keneged
avodot hamishkan*, we taught like the one that says that it corresponds
to the work they did in the משכן Mishkan *Mishkan*.
Where? דתניא *De-tanya*, we taught in the ברייתא *Baraita*. אין חייבין אלא
המלאכה שהייתה כיוצא בה במשכן *Ein chayavin ela hamelacha she-hayeta kayotze bah
bamishkan*, you're only חייב *chayav* of a מלאכה melacha. *melacha* that you
found something parallel to it that that type of מלאכה melacha. *melacha*
was done in the משכן Mishkan. *Mishkan*. הם זרעו *Hem zaru*, they
planted, ואתם לא תזרעו *v'atem lo tizre'u*, you don't plant. הם קצרו
*Hem katzru*, they harvested, ואתם לא תקצרו *v'atem lo tiktzoru*, you don't
harvest. הם העלו את הקרשים מקרקע לעגלה *Hem he'elu et hakarashim mikarka
la-agala*, they took the beams from the ground to the wagon, which
is a רשות היחיד *reshut hayachid*, the ground was a רשות הרבים
*reshut harabim*, ואתם לא תכניסו מרשות הרבים לרשות היחיד *v'atem lo tachnisu
mereshut harabim lereshut hayachid*,
don't go from רשות הרבים *reshut harabim* to רשות היחיד *reshut hayachid*.
הם הורידו את הקרשים מהעגלה לקרקע *Hem horidu et hakarashim me-ha-agala lakarka*,
they took them off of the wagon onto the ground, ואתם לא
תוציאו מרשות היחיד לרשות הרבים *v'atem lo totzi'u mereshut hayachid lereshut harabim*,
you don't take from private domain to public. הם הוציאו מעגלה לעגלה
*Hem hotzi'u me-agala le-agala*, they transferred from one wagon to the other
with a street between them, ואתם לא תוציאו מרשות היחיד לרשות היחיד
*v'atem lo totzi'u mereshut hayachid lereshut hayachid*, you don't hand something from
one רשות היחיד *reshut hayachid* to another רשות היחיד *reshut hayachid*. מרשות
היחיד לרשות היחיד *Mereshut hayachid lereshut hayachid*, so the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*
says מרשות היחיד לרשות היחיד מאי קעביד *mereshut hayachid lereshut hayachid mai
k'avid*, who cares if you go from one רשות היחיד *reshut hayachid*
to another one? So אביי ורבא דאמרי תרוייהו ואיתימא רב אדא בר
אהבה *Abaye v'Rava d'amrei t'vayehu v'itayma Rav Adda bar Ahava*, no, here's
what it means. מרשות היחיד לרשות היחיד דרך רשות הרבים *Mereshut hayachid
lereshut hayachid derech reshut harabim*, you hand from one רשות היחיד *reshut
hayachid* to the other and there's a רשות הרבים *reshut harabim* in
between. That's a special מלאכה melacha *melacha* that is called like הושטה
*hoshata* or whatever because we learned it in the first פרקים *perakim*
because of the issues of the משכן Mishkan *Mishkan*. Now I want
to sort of start with some small points and then make bigger
points. Small point number one is you'll notice of the things that
they're mentioning of מלאכה melacha *melacha*, three out of the five were
carrying. It's a little crazy. So this goes back to the point
תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* made at the beginning of the מסכת *masechet* that
carrying in a way is the weakest מלאכה melacha *melacha* because it's
not productive labor and therefore you can't so much focus on the
outcome. By other מלאכות melachot *melachot* you can focus on what are
you producing. By carrying you have to focus on the act. So
therefore you need a model for the separate types of acts. You
know,
by other things like if you can't cook you also can't bake
and you also can't fry, but by carrying it's about the act
and therefore maybe only רשות היחיד *reshut hayachid* to רשות הרבים *reshut
harabim* is אסור *assur*, maybe the reverse isn't the problem. So each
special separate act has to have a paradigm, has to have in
the משכן Mishkan. *Mishkan*. So that's just that. Now while we're talking
about the specific things, it talks about planting and harvesting. Where did
they plant, where did they harvest in the building of the משכן
Mishkan *Mishkan*? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says that it's about the making
of the dyes. You have to plant the stuff to get, you
know dyes come from various plants. You have to plant, you have
to harvest them. And so where did they cook or bake in
the making of the משכן Mishkan *Mishkan*? So רש"י *Rashi* says no,
they cooked for producing the dyes. You take the dyes, you put
them in some type of solution, you put over a fire you
extract, you extract the dye. So that's what רש"י *Rashi* says. רש"י
*Rashi* is saying all of this because רש"י *Rashi* says that the
making of the משכן Mishkan *Mishkan* means the משכן Mishkan *Mishkan* means
the making of the משכן Mishkan. *Mishkan*. There's a position of the
גאונים Gaonim *Geonim* that says no, we're talking about planting and harvesting
and baking that you would do for making like the לחם הפנים
*lechem hapanim*, making for various types of, you know making for for
the מנחות *menachot*, for the grain breads that you would bring, you
would bring in the משכן Mishkan. *Mishkan*. So that approach says that
you can learn for the model of the מלאכות melachot *melachot* not
just what they did for the building of the משכן Mishkan? *Mishkan*
but what they actually did in the bringing of the sacrifices for
the daily עבודה avoda *avodah*. But that's a big problem because we
don't learn from the daily sacrifices, like we don't learn שחיטה *shechita*
from the fact that they would שחטו קרבן *shechtu korban*, which would
be the obvious place if it was based on it. Right? We
learn שחיטה *shechita* from the way they would squeeze out these fish
or snails and make and they would squeeze the blood out in
order to make תכלת *techelet*. So it seems like we really don't
learn from the קרבנות korbanot, *korbanot*, we learn from the making of
the משכן Mishkan *Mishkan*. So the אגלי טל *Eglei Tal* who is
a,
it's a very important ספר *sefer* on the ל"ט מלאכות melachot *lamed
tet melachot* in his introduction he discusses this debate. And he basically
claims, tries to claim, that the position that says we learn it
out from the bringing of the קרבנות korbanot *korbanot* really means only
the קרבנות *korbanot* that you could only, the things that you couldn't
do on שבת Shabbat. *Shabbat*. If you could do it on שבת
*Shabbat*, if you could שחט shocht *shecht* an animal on שבת *Shabbat*,
there's no proof that that was a
מלאכה melacha *melacha*. The reason we know that the making of the
משכן Mishkan, *Mishkan* is a מלאכה melacha *melacha* is because you don't
make the משכן Mishkan, *Mishkan* on שבת *Shabbat*. So therefore we say
everything that went into the making of the משכן Mishkan. *Mishkan* we
can infer that was a מלאכה melacha *melacha* and the proof being
you don't do it on שבת *Shabbat*. So therefore by the קרבנות
*korbanot* as well since you do them on שבת *Shabbat*, they cannot
serve as a model for the מלאכה melacha, *melacha*. But there are
some things you don't do on שבת *Shabbat*. You don't plant the
grain for the לחם הפנים *lechem hapanim* on שבת *Shabbat*. Okay. So
those you can use as a model, certain things even in the
bringing of קרבנות *korbanot* as long as they weren't done on שבת
*Shabbat* can also be a model for the ל"ט מלאכות melachot. *lamed
tet melachot*. We tend to assume like רש"י *Rashi*. ל"ט מלאכות melachot
*lamed tet melachot* are learned from the making of the משכן Mishkan,
*Mishkan*, not from the sacrifices or the various offerings of the משכן
Mishkan? *Mishkan*. Now I want to get to the bigger question about
what is this source of the ל"ט So let's first talk about
this מלאכת meleches מלאכתו, melachto? how do you get 39? So right
at the outset, the גאונים Geonim recognize that there's much more than
39 times it says מלאכה. melacha, רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel counts 61,
you can look inside. He has some way of eliminating 21 of
them, getting down to the 40 and then the גמרא Gemara eliminates
the last one. Okay, and all the ראשונים Rishonim try to do
a big counting and figure out what type of logic can you
get to the 40 of the גמרא. Gemara גמרא Gemara seems that
there was 40 and it only had to eliminate one. So anyway
there’s this assumption starting with רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel that there were
61. So there’s this wonderful article by רב יואל בן נון Rav
Yoel Bin-Nun who has a great approach to explaining this whole idea
of how you get to it, but I'll tell you in a
minute. But anyway, but he says that he mentions that the son
of the תוספות יום טוב Tosafos Yom Tov basically pointed out once
there was a concordance, which was made by actually the non-Jews came
out with the first concordance, that actually made it a lot easier
but they didn't have בר אילן Bar Ilan yet. Anyway, so he’s
able to find that there weren't even 61, there were 65. So
anyway all the ways that they got down from 61 to 40
don't work anymore because actually he was able to actually identify that
there were 65. So it’s a big problem, how do you get
40? So what רב יואל בן נון Rav Yoel Bin-Nun says is,
his approach is, and I want you to look, here I made
some sheets for you. Okay. So first if you look at the
flip side of the page, the two columns.
He says when it says כנגד מלאכת המשכן, k'neged meleches hamishkan,
it really meant
what it really meant originally is, look at the flip side, the
side of the two columns, is when in ויקהל Vayakhel and פקודי
Pekudei where it lists all the things that they would that they
made: את המשכן את אהלו את מכסהו את קרסיו את קרשיו את
בריחיו את עמודיו, es hamishkan es oholo es michseihu es krasav es
krashav es berichav es amudav, right? And if you look at the
two lists, there’s some variations of the list, but ultimately but basically
whatever the variations are and he explains why there are those variations,
each list has 39 items. And the last two he says are
really just explaining the בגדי השרד. bigdei hasrad. בגדי השרד לשרת בקודש.
bigdei hasrad l'shares bakodesh. What were the בגדי השרד? bigdei hasrad? את
בגדי הקודש לאהרן הכהן ואת בגדי בניו לכהן. es bigdei hakodesh l'Aharon
hakohen v'es bigdei vanav l'chahen. But that really both lists have 39
and that when it says כנגד מלאכת המשכן k'neged meleches hamishkan it
meant the actual items that were produced and that was our basis
for the number 39. Now that is inconvenient because תוספות Tosafos asks
an obvious question. תוספות Tosafos says I don’t get it. He says
how can you say the משכן Mishkan. without saying 39? Wonderful, you
gave your answer which was where do we get the number from?
We get it from the משכן. Mishkan, That doesn't tell me where
we get the number from. That just tells me where we learn
you know what are the מלאכות melachot what are they. But as
תוספות Tosafos: points out we actually work very hard to get to
39. Look at this little תוספות: Tosafos ארבעים
אבות מלאכה חסר אחת כנגד מי. arba'im avos melacha chaser achas k'neged
mi. He says דהרבה מלאכות אי דדמיין להדדי. d'harbei melachos i d'damin
l'hadadi. There are many מלאכות melachot. of these 39 that we would
have all they’re very similar. We would have put them all in
the same category. והוי לן למיחשבינהו כולהו כחדא v'havi lan l'michsevin kullah
k'achas and we should have all really made like five different מלאכות
melachot called them one. כפרעי דרי כלא כדא. k'par'ei d'rei k'la k'da.
היינו זורה היינו בורר היינו מרקד. hainu zoreh hainu borer hainu merakid.
Whether you’re talking about winnowing or selecting or sifting, it’s all basically
the same מלאכה. melacha? It’s selecting the good from the bad. But
we have this as three separate מלאכות. melachot So clearly משום חילוק
משהו
שביניהם mishum chilluk mashehu shebeineihem because of some subtle difference, לא הוינן
מחלקינן להו lo havin machalkinan lehu we would not have made them
separate categories אי לאו דקיימא
לן דל"ט מלאכות הן כנגד
שום דבר ilav d'kama lan d'lamed-tet melachos hein k'neged shum davar unless
we had established that we had a number of 39. So תוספות
Tosafos says very interestingly we clearly start with the 39 and we
have to work to get to it. So even if you know
our model is the משכן Mishkan. that doesn't would not necessarily lead
to 39 categories. It might have led to 28 categories, it might
have led to 32. But we knew we had to get to
39 and therefore we made small divisions in order to get to
39. Okay, that makes a lot of sense. But now it begs
the question. גמרא Gemara says where do you get the 39 from?
You get it from the first answer is you get it from
the משכן. Mishkan. But that doesn't tell you 39. So תוספות Tosafot
tries to say maybe the two answers are both agreeing with one
another but he admits that that’s not true. גמרא Gemara. makes it
clear that there’s a difference. So therefore what so therefore that’s what
רב יואל בן נון Rav Yoel Bin-Nun comes along and he says.
The one that says we learn it from the משכן Mishkan. is
also giving you a number of 39.
We learn it from the משכן Mishkan. not just that we get
the concept of מלאכה melacha from the משכן Mishkan. but how do
we get the number 39? You get that from the משכן Mishkan
as well when you count all the items in the משכן. Mishkan,
So that’s first of all a beautiful explanation that he gives to
the first approach that we get it from the משכן. Mishkan. How
about the second approach of מלאכה melacha מלאכת meleches מלאכתו? melachto. So
there he says if in the if you look in early manuscripts
of the גמרא Gemara it doesn't have the three words: מלאכה melacha.
מלאכת meleches. מלאכתו. melachto, It only has מלאכה melacha and מלאכת. meleches
And if actually you just look at those two words, or actually
he says if מלאכה melacha? and מלאכתו, melachto, then you actually do
get the 40 of the גמרא. Gemara So by eliminating one of
those three words you actually get the 40 and one of them
snuck in. So he says that it was מלאכה melacha. and מלאכתו,
melachto those will give you 40, those two without מלאכת melachet will
give you 40. Okay, so that’s his explanation of this. So now
I just... There's one other very important issue I want to touch
on. What have we said so far?
First we said that a couple of important things. Number one, where
do you learn it from the משכן? Mishkan. רש"י says it's the
building. Some גאונים say even the bringing of the קרבנות, but modified
by קרבנות that you couldn't bring, things you couldn't do on שבת.
That's where you get that from. What is the idea of you
getting it from the תוספות Tosafot says clearly we start with the
number 39 even after we knew משכן because we're going to make
subtle divisions in order to get to that number of 39. So
when the גמרא Gemara. says משכן, it still doesn't give me the
answer of 39. תוספות Tosafot would like to say the two answers
work together, but it's clear from the גמרא Gemara, they don't. So
how if you have the first answer of משכן, do you get
39? So there, as I shared with you this beautiful approach of
רב יואל בן נון Rav Yoel Bin-Nun that gets 39 straight from
the משכן. If you have מלאכה, melacha. מלאכתו melachto, and you count,
how do you get 39? There's many more. Another nice answer he
says is that if you use two of the words and not
three, you'll get that number as well. Now the one question we're
left with, and this is key is, if you're learning it from
מלאכה, מלאכתו, melachto. מלאכת melachet, and not from the משכן,
then where do you get the idea what counts as a מלאכה?
Is it really possible we got that idea of what counts as
a מלאכה not from the משכן? So תוספות Tosafot rejects this out
of hand. If you look at תוספות כנגד כל מלאכה שבתורה, Tosafot
Keneged Kol Melacha SheBaTorah, תוספות Tosafot says, לכאורה נראה דיליף נמי ממשכן,
lechora nireh deyulif nami miMishkan,
even the one that's doing the counting of מלאכת, presumably he's learning
from the משכן. שכן סמך פרשת שבת לפרשת משכן. sheken samach parshat
Shabbat leparshat Mishkan.
First of all, that's why they're always juxtaposed. ועוד דאי לא יליף
ממשכן אם כן היכי ידעינן לדידיה הני אבות מלאכות והני תולדות. ve-od
de-i lo yalif miMishkan im ken heichi yadinan ledidei hani avot melachot
vehani toldot.
Then where would we ever know, if you're not using the משכן,
what constitutes a מלאכה or not? דאנן סברא לן דאין סברא לומר
שמידעתם
ביררו מלאכות החשובות ועשאום אבות. da-anan savra lan de-ein savra lomar she-mida'atam
bereru melachot ha-chashuvot ve-asu-um avot. It doesn't make sense that חז"ל Chazal
just picked what they thought made sense was a מלאכה. Presumably everybody
has to agree you get it from the משכן. So תוספות Tosafot
would like to read these two approaches combined, but he admits that
you really can't in the גמרא. So what תוספות says it would
be absurd to think that you would actually have determined the מלאכות
melachot without the model of the משכן. But lo and behold, one
of the בעלי התוספות, Ba'alei HaTosafot, the יראים, Yereim, רבי אליעזר ממיץ
Rabbi Eliezer miMetz who was a תלמיד talmid of רבנו תם Rabbeinu
Tam says exactly that. And if you look at the sheet I
just handed out, the first paragraph, okay, he says
the first section, the third paragraph: ואמרינן בשבת בפרק במה טומנין הני
אבות מלאכות כנגד מי אמר רבי חנינה בר חמא כנגד עבודת המשכן
רבי יונתן בן אלעזר אומר בן לוקניא אומר
כנגד מלאכה ומלאכות שבתורה. ve-amrinan beShabbat beperek Bameh Tomnin hani avot melachot
keneged mi amar Rabbi Chanina bar Chama keneged avodot haMishkan Rabbi Yonatan
ben Elazar omer ben Lukunya omer keneged melacha umelachot shebaTorah. And by
the way, how many words does he have? כנגד two, מלאכה and
מלאכות melachot. or מלאכתו. He does not have all three words, right?
There you go. That makes life a lot easier. Anyway, ארבעים חסר
אחת. arba'im chaser achat. So now according to that approach, where do
you get what constitutes a מלאכה? וראו חכמים אלו מלאכות הדומות עבודה
הדומה היא הנקראת מלאכה. ve-ra'u chachamim elu melachot ha-domot avoda ha-doma hi
ha-nikret melacha. The rabbis saw what type of thing would constitute like
work, and that would be a מלאכה. דכתיב מלאכת עבודה לא תעשו.
de-chtiv melachat avoda lo ta'asu. It has to be some type of
thing that's עבודה-like. ואמרינן אלו הן שהקפידה התורה עליהם. ve-amrinan elu hen
she-hikpida haTorah aleihem. And they said that would be the ones the
Torah's talking about. כי לא מסרן הכתוב אלא לחכמים
והם ראויים להיקרא מלאכה. ki lo masran ha-katuv ela le-chachamim ve-hem re'uyim
le-hikarei melacha. It was totally up to the sages to determine what
constitutes a מלאכה. So talk about that, about shattering everything we've always
been taught, that absolutely comes from the משכן. According to the יראים,
Yereim, the second approach doesn't mention משכן. The rabbis were told don't
do work, the Torah says don't do work, 39 categories, you guys
figure out what constitutes work. And they figured out for themselves these
39 things that make sense for the categories of work, nothing to
do with the משכן. Now that is very important because
it
answers a very important issue which I'll remind you of when we
get to כלל גדול, Klal Gadol, the seventh perek, which lists the
39 מלאכות. melachot But when the 39 מלאכות Melachot, are listed, they
are not listed in any משכן organization. They are listed, they are
organized by certain types of crafts. So for example, the first 11
מלאכות is how do you get to making baking bread? You plant,
you harvest, you sift, you know, you winnow, you grind, you knead,
you bake. 11 מלאכות that get you to baking bread. The next
list is how do you get to making garments? So you shear,
you comb, you weave, right, you snip. That's the second group. How
do you get to making
parchment and writing? So you שחט an animal, you skin it, you
work the cloth, you make the lines, you write, and that's your
next list of מלאכות. So all the list, how do you get
to building buildings, right? So or that talks about the construction. So
all the lists of the מלאכות are basically four or five categories
of the separate stages in particular crafts. And that works very nicely,
it could just be a mnemonic, it could be, yeah, we get
it from the משכן, but here's a nice way of organizing it.
But it works very well according to the יראים Yereim who says
maybe it's not based on the משכן. חז"ל Chazal looked and they
said what constitutes the type of, you know, daily work that people
do? Look at the various crafts that they do. They make, you
know, cloth, they make... They bake bread and all these types of
things, and those are the 39 מלאכות, those various stages. So it's
a quite radical different approach to where we get the number 39
from, but he learns it straight from this גמרא, one approach that
does not mention משכן. Yes.
So yeah, because I was actually...
You know, let's end here. You can ask me your question after.